One hallmark of writing good code is ensuring
an app does not crash due to a runtime error.
Many programming languages, Python included,
have keywords we can use to attempt to run
code, control the error message displayed
if the code would otherwise cause a crash,
and then run certain logic depending on whether
the original intent to run code worked.
This concept of controlling errors and their
messages is known as exception handling.
To start this exception handling process,
we have a project in this 521-try file, where,
on line 1, we have a list of figuratives for
language, five to be exact.
And then, on line 3, we have code to get someone
to input a number from 1 to 5 to get further
information on one of the five figuratives.
On line 6, I have a formatted print statement
to print the figurative someone requested.
On line four, we assign the number to the
index value of whatever figurative was chosen.
Why the -1?
Remember that lists are zero-based, so these
five figuratives have an index of 0 through
4.
Asking someone to type that in could confuse
one trying to run the app.
Thus, we can have one enter a number 1 through
5 and then subtract 1 from that entry to fit
the parameters of our zero-based list.
I will run the code and enter a legitimate
number.
That code works as expected.
Next, I will rerun the code and enter a bad
value.
The result returns an index out of range error,
known as an IndexError, as the number we submitted
is out of the range of items in the list.
While that error message is descriptive, it
will not make sense to most, hence the need
to control an error message.
In this case, the first step in exception
handling is to add a try block to the code
we are trying to run, lines 3 and 4.
On line 2, I will type try and a colon, and
then indent lines 3 and 4 so that they sit
in this try block.
A try block cannot run by itself, so we will
not run the code here.
It's important to note that a try block usually
has at least an except block to catch exceptions
and often includes a finally block to execute
code regardless of whether an exception occurs.
Sometimes, it also includes an else block.
However, a try block cannot run without at
least a finally or except block accompanying
it.
The try block tells the app to run a code
block, hopefully without errors.
In the following two topics, we will see how
to account for an error within the try block
and when the code in a try block causes no
errors.